<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC3629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5741 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5741.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6949 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6949.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.flanagan-nonascii SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.flanagan-nonascii.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.flanagan-rfc-framework SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.flanagan-rfc-framework.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-flanagan-plaintext-03" ipr="trust200902">

<!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

<front>
<!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the full title is longer than 39 characters -->

  <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">Requirements for Plain-Text RFCs</title>
  <author fullname="Heather Flanagan" initials="H." surname="Flanagan">
    <organization>RFC Editor</organization>

    <address>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>rse@rfc-editor.org</email>
    </address>
  </author>

<<<<<<< HEAD:draft-flanagan-plaintext.xml
    <date day="29" month="September" year="2014" />
=======
  <date day="22" month="September" year="2014" />
>>>>>>> FETCH_HEAD:draft-flanagan-plaintext-03.xml

  <area>General</area>

  <keyword>RFC</keyword>
  <keyword>ASCII</keyword>
  <keyword>format</keyword>
  <keyword>plain-text</keyword>
  <keyword>plain text</keyword>

  <abstract>
      <t>In 2013, after a great deal of community discussion, the decision 
      was made to shift from the plain-text, ASCII-only canonical format to 
      XML.  The high-level requirements for the format of RFCs were defined 
      in RFC6949, "RFC Series Format Requirements and Future Development."  
      Several different publication formats will be rendered from that 
      canonical XML, including HTML, PDF, TXT, and EPUB.  This draft documents 
      the change in requirements and layout for the plain-text RFC publication 
      format.</t>
  </abstract>
  <note title="Editorial Note (To be removed by the RFC Editor)">
    <t>Discussion of this draft takes place on the rfc-interest mailing list
      (rfc-interest@rfc-editor.org), which has its home page at
      https://www.rfc-editor.org/mailman/listinfo/rfc-interest.
    </t>
  </note>
</front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The decision was made in May 2013 to shift from the plain-text, 
      ASCII-only canonical format to 
      XML <xref target="XML-ANNOUNCE"/>.  The high-level requirements for 
      the format of RFCs were defined in <xref target="RFC6949">"RFC Series 
      Format Requirements and Future Development" </xref>.  Several different 
      publication formats will be rendered from that canonical XML, including 
      HTML, PDF, TXT, and EPUB <xref target="I-D.flanagan-rfc-framework"/>. </t>

      <t>The Unicode Consortium defines 'plain text' as 
      <xref target="unicode-glossary">"Computer-encoded text that consists 
      only of a sequence of code points from a given standard, with no 
      other formatting or structural information.  Plain text interchange is 
      commonly used between computer systems that do not share higher-level 
      protocols." </xref></t>

      <t>A plain-text output for RFCs will continue to be required
      for the foreseeable future.  The details of what that means for RFCs in 
      terms of which character encoding may be used, what the page layout 
      will look like, how to handle figures and artwork, and how pagination 
      will be handled, are documented in this memo.</t>

      <t>The following assumptions drive the changes in the plain-text
      output for RFCs:</t>
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>The existing tools used by the RFC Editor and many members
              of the author community to create the text file are complicated
              to change and support; manual manipulation is often required 
              for the final output.  In particular, handling page breaks and 
              associated widows and orphans for paginated output is tricky.</t>
              <t>Additional publication formats--for example: PDF, HTML--
              will be available that will offer features such as markup, 
              pretty printing, etc. </t> 
              <t>There is an extensive tool chain in existence among the 
              community to work with plain-text documents.  Similar 
              functionality may be possible with other publication formats, 
              but the workflow that uses the existing tool chain should be 
              supported as much as is considered practical.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
      <t>Where practical, the original guidance for the structure of a 
      plain-text RFC has been kept, such as with line lengths, lines per 
      page, etc. <xref target="INS2AUTH"/></t>

      <t>Note that this document provides guidance for plain-text RFCs; 
      Internet-Drafts are out of scope.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Character Encoding">
      <t>Plain-text files for RFCs will use the 
      <xref target="RFC3629">UTF-8</xref> character encoding.  That said, 
      the use of non-ASCII characters will be only allowed in a limited and
      controlled fashion.  The details regarding the guidance for how to 
      include non-ASCII characters is under development and documented in
      <xref target="I-D.flanagan-nonascii">"The Use of Non-ASCII 
      Characters in RFCs"</xref>.  Please view the PDF version of that draft.</t>

      <t>The plain-text file will include a byte order 
      mark (BOM) to provide text reader software with in-band information
      about the character encoding scheme used. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Figures and Artwork">
      <t>Authors may continue to include figures drawn with ASCII characters.  
      If the canonical format includes figures or artwork other than ASCII-art,
      then the plain-text output must include a pointer to the relevant figure 
      in the HTML version of the RFC to allow readers to see the relevant 
      artwork.</t>

      <t>Authors who wish to include ASCII-art for the plain-text file and 
      SVG art for the other outputs may do so, but they should be aware of the
      potential for confusion to individuals reading the RFC with two unique
      diagrams describing the same content.  If there is conflicting 
      information between the publication formats, please review the XML or 
      PDF files to resolve the conflict.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="General Page Format Layout">
       <t>One plain-text output will be created during the publication
       process with basic pagination that includes a form feed instruction 
       every 58 lines at most, including blank lines.  Instructions or a 
       script will be made available by and for the community to strip out 
       pagination as per individual preference. </t>

        <section title="Headers and Footers">
          <t>The front matter on the front page (such as the RFC number 
          and category), and the back matter on the last page (the author's 
          full names and contact information) will continue with the 
          structure described in <xref target="RFC5741">RFC 5741</xref>, 
          "RFC Streams, Headers, and Boilerplates".  Given the removal of the 
          pagination requirement, running headers and footers will no 
          longer exist.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Table of Contents">
          <t>Given the removal of the pagination requirement, the Table of 
          Contents will list section and subsection numbers and titles, but 
          will not include page numbers.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Line Width">
          <t>Each line must be limited to 72 characters followed by the
          character sequence that denotes an end-of-line (EOL).  This
          limit includes any left-side indentation.</t>

          <t>Note: A plain-text RFC is expected to be stored on a
          disk file using the EOL sequence of that system.  For
          example, MS DOS-based systems use the two-character
          sequence: CR LF (Carriage Return followed by Line Feed),
          Unix systems use the single character LF for EOL, and
          EBCDIC systems use the single character NL (New Line).</t>

          <t>Whenever an RFC is transmitted across the Internet,
          Internet protocol convention requires that each line of
          text be followed by the two-character EOL sequence CR LF
          (Carriage Return followed by Line Feed).  A user level
          protocol (e.g., FTP, Telnet, HTTP, SMTP, ...) must make
          the appropriate EOL transformation at each line end.
          Note that binary transmission of plain-text RFC files
          can cause the sender's EOL convention to "leak" into the
          receiver, causing confusion.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Line Spacing">
          <t>Use single-spaced text within a paragraph, and one blank line
           between paragraphs.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Hyphenation">
          <t>Hyphenated words, including hyphenated word sequences (e.g.,
          "Internet-Draft"), should not be split across successive lines.
          </t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This draft owes a great deal of thanks to the efforts of the RFC 
      Format Design Team: Nevil Brownlee, Tony Hansen, Joe Hildebrand, Paul 
      Hoffman, Ted Lemon, Julian Reschke, Adam Roach, Alice Russo, Robert 
      Sparks, and David Thaler.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no requests to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>

  <section anchor="Changes" title="Change Log for the Draft">
    <section anchor="changes3" title="-02 to -03">
      <t>Abstract: expanded</t>
      <t>Introduction: adjusted language of assumptions</t>
      <t>Figures and Artwork: adjusted to indicate where to go in case information for the images conflicts between different formats</t>
    </section>
  </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC3629;
      &RFC5741;
      &RFC6949;
      &I-D.flanagan-nonascii;
      &I-D.flanagan-rfc-framework;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="unicode-glossary"
                 target="http://www.unicode.org/glossary/">
        <front>
          <title>Glossary of Unicode Terms</title>
          <author>
            <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2014" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="INS2AUTH"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc-editor/instructions2authors.txt">
         <front>
           <title>Instructions to Request for Comments (RFC) Authors</title>
           <author>
             <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
           </author>
           <date month="August" year="2004" />
         </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="XML-ANNOUNCE"
       target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/pipermail/rfc-interest/2013-May/005584.html
">
        <front>
          <title>"Subject: Direction of the RFC Format Development effort", message to the rfc-interest@rfc-editor.org mailing list</title>
          <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan">
             <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="May" day="2" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>

